<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Aoife's Blog</title><link>/</link><description>Recent content on Aoife's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 20:09:47 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Poem01</title><link>/posts/poem01/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 20:09:47 +0100</pubDate><guid>/posts/poem01/</guid><description>Waste away your life
and all your past lives
all these things that push me
are not things that should worry me
Fill this head with ideas,
that convince her you&amp;rsquo;re not real
you&amp;rsquo;re just someone who lives in a bottom in your attic
and now we&amp;rsquo;re both empty</description></item><item><title>Poem00</title><link>/posts/poem00/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 19:28:50 +0100</pubDate><guid>/posts/poem00/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m in a mirror, swimming at night.
Those numbers are just null and void to me now
They buried your mother, but you are just a face now
Hooks held down, now set you loose
We could have went forward through the night
but I took a now strangers car.
Biggest regret is about the guitar
sunburnt and childhood dreamed. It could have been mine
Mind games, I hoped were smarter.</description></item><item><title>September 2022</title><link>/posts/september2022/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 18:32:02 +0100</pubDate><guid>/posts/september2022/</guid><description>“And so with the sunshine and the great bursts of leaves growing on the trees, just as things grow in fast movies, I had that familiar conviction that life was beginning over again with the summer.”
Summary The title of this blog may be “September”, but it&amp;rsquo;s really more of a summary of things for the last few months.
Where to start?
Hmmm. Maybe a little honesty and insight is useful.</description></item><item><title>Top 5 Games 2021</title><link>/posts/top-5-games-2021/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2021 17:40:54 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/top-5-games-2021/</guid><description>About this list! Before I list my top games of 2021 I want to make clear that this is purely a list of the games which I enjoyed the most in 2021. Meaning a few of the games released quite a few years prior. These aren&amp;rsquo;t reviews, and I will avoid spoilers!
(Here is a full video of this article on my YouTube channel)
# 5. Chivalry 2. Most nights, when I have time to play games, I don&amp;rsquo;t have the energy for story heavy or intense gameplay sessions.</description></item><item><title>A review of Marvel Champions the Living Card Game</title><link>/posts/marvel-champions-review/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2021 19:23:09 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/marvel-champions-review/</guid><description>Intro Marvel champions is the latest living card game (LCG) from fantasy flight games. If you are familiar with other entries in this series of games, such as Arkham Horror The Card Game, then not much introduction is needed. These games come with a core set that gets you started and allows/encourages you to expand your gameplay through additional expansion packs. Unlike some games on the market, these LCGs and their expansions are not randomised and you always know what you’re getting in your box/card pack.</description></item><item><title>Computational Modelling with Apple Silicon</title><link>/posts/m1modelling/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Nov 2021 15:15:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/m1modelling/</guid><description>Ever since Apple Silicon was announced I was enthralled and curious. Even as reviews and benchmarks came pouring in after the original M1 Macbook Pro, Mini and Air released I was skeptical. Working in research we often find that tools we depend on are ancient by computer standards, even worse is that some of them are either difficult to build/update or are closed source (or worse still, written in PERL!). Which highlights my major fear of Apple&amp;rsquo;s new direction, I was initially terrified that almost all of my pipelines and tools would die in x86 and I would be forced to migrate to, ugh, Windows.</description></item><item><title>Visualising World Temperature Data</title><link>/posts/temp-data/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Nov 2021 00:57:10 +0100</pubDate><guid>/posts/temp-data/</guid><description>I like to start with the end result of a project, just to show if this is what you&amp;rsquo;re looking for before you read:
Some caveats:
These data are limited to what a 10 second google search yielded (I found it on Kaggle) Data are approximately matched to country codes in order to streamline things Year range of data is very limited Code is written in an obtuse way in order to make clear what is happening There is little need for multiple lists matching data codes for example Some countries are missing data, easily solved with better country code matching and a better data source Libraries required for this:</description></item><item><title>Narrow Escape Visualization</title><link>/posts/narrow-escape/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 13:45:50 +0100</pubDate><guid>/posts/narrow-escape/</guid><description>The Narrow Escape Problem is a bio physics problem which attempts to estimate how long it takes for a particle moving under Brownian motion to escape from a container with solid walls, where part of the wall is open.
Recently we published a software library for building narrow escape simulations. We also used this to discuss its use in determining the escape time for small molecules from plant cells.
I&amp;rsquo;ve recently been working with plotly to create interactive plots.</description></item><item><title>Hello World</title><link>/posts/hello-world/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 13:28:26 +0100</pubDate><guid>/posts/hello-world/</guid><description>Hi, Thanks for coming to my new blog.
I hope to soon populate it with lots of fun things.</description></item><item><title>Skyrim Randomiser</title><link>/randomsky/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 13:07:22 +0100</pubDate><guid>/randomsky/</guid><description> Number of Main Quests to complete: 1 Number of Skills to main: 6 Number of Challenges to Attempt: 0 Click "Generate" to get a randomized challenge for Skyrim.
Generate Reset Your Quest(s) and Character: Main Quests to complete Skills Character Race Misc Challenges</description></item></channel></rss>