<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Aoife's Blog</title><link>/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Aoife's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 20:09:47 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Poem01</title><link>/posts/poem01/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 20:09:47 +0100</pubDate><guid>/posts/poem01/</guid><description>Waste away your life
and all your past lives
all these things that push me
are not things that should worry me
Fill this head with ideas,
that convince her you&amp;rsquo;re not real
you&amp;rsquo;re just someone who lives in a bottom in your attic
and now we&amp;rsquo;re both empty</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Waste away your life</p>
<p>and all your past lives</p>
<p>all these things that push me</p>
<p>are not things that should worry me</p>
<p>Fill this head with ideas,</p>
<p>that convince her you&rsquo;re not real</p>
<p>you&rsquo;re just someone who lives in a bottom in your attic</p>
<p>and now we&rsquo;re both empty</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Poem00</title><link>/posts/poem00/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 19:28:50 +0100</pubDate><guid>/posts/poem00/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m in a mirror, swimming at night.
Those numbers are just null and void to me now
They buried your mother, but you are just a face now
Hooks held down, now set you loose
We could have went forward through the night
but I took a now strangers car.
Biggest regret is about the guitar
sunburnt and childhood dreamed. It could have been mine
Mind games, I hoped were smarter.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m in a mirror, swimming at night.</p>
<p>Those numbers are just null and void to me now</p>
<p>They buried your mother, but you are just a face now</p>
<p>Hooks held down, now set you loose</p>
<p>We could have went forward through the night</p>
<p>but I took a now strangers car.</p>
<p>Biggest regret is about the guitar</p>
<p>sunburnt and childhood dreamed. It could have been mine</p>
<p>Mind games, I hoped were smarter.</p>
<p>They could have just been tessellating chocolate bars.</p>
<p>Lessons of loved burned in.</p>
<p>Taught that I didn&rsquo;t need him</p>
<p>That resilience just passed onto you</p>
<p>and you&rsquo;re just a face to me now.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>September 2022</title><link>/posts/september2022/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 18:32:02 +0100</pubDate><guid>/posts/september2022/</guid><description>“And so with the sunshine and the great bursts of leaves growing on the trees, just as things grow in fast movies, I had that familiar conviction that life was beginning over again with the summer.”
Summary The title of this blog may be “September”, but it&amp;rsquo;s really more of a summary of things for the last few months.
Where to start?
Hmmm. Maybe a little honesty and insight is useful.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>“And so with the sunshine and the great bursts of leaves growing on the trees, just as things grow in fast movies, I had that familiar conviction that life was beginning over again with the summer.”</p>
</blockquote>
<h1 id="summary">Summary</h1>
<p>The title of this blog may be “September”, but it&rsquo;s really more of a summary of
things for the last few months.</p>
<p>Where to start?</p>
<p>Hmmm. Maybe a little honesty and insight is useful. Prior to August 2022 I thought it
was perfectly normal to have a general distaste for life, and that we all just
went through because of some strange biological compulsion. What I am trying to
stress here is that for the first time in 28 years I have become happy.</p>
<p>When I started my new job, I quickly realised that my demeanour had changed
significantly. My reactive responses to questions became different. When asked
&ldquo;how are you?&rdquo; my old response would be &ldquo;Fine, thanks, you?&rdquo;, now I find myself
saying &ldquo;Fantastic! You?&rdquo;. Whilst this may seem silly and trivial it is something
that I could not help but say, and that is how I realised that life can be good.</p>
<h1 id="what-changed">What changed?</h1>
<p>Why am I compelled to be happy?</p>
<p>Well, I don&rsquo;t have to be stressed any more. I finally feel like my life has
started to be worth something. This change has come about through three
shakeups:</p>
<ol>
<li>PhD is done</li>
<li>I have my dream job</li>
<li>Moved to London</li>
</ol>
<p>Doing the PhD was one of the best things I have done with my life, but OH GOD am
I glad it&rsquo;s dead.</p>
<h2 id="phds-are-unsuitable-for-humans">PhD&rsquo;s are unsuitable for humans</h2>
<p>Allow me to be perfectly clear: my supervisor, friends and most of the people I
interacted with during my studies are amazing people and have been lovely to me.
But, there is something&hellip; something I can&rsquo;t quite perfectly explain. Maybe it&rsquo;s
the unspoken (sometimes) expectation within academia to overwork, or the
<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-022-03069-w">disgusting</a> salaries paid
to the backbone of our academic system, the PhD students. Maybe it&rsquo;s the
uncertainty? It could even be the loneliness. Yes, as a student I was surrounded
by caring people, but they had their projects and I had mine. Sometimes we
worked adjacent to one another, but we each had very specific things which we
owned. Perhaps it&rsquo;s the feeling of simultaneously being expected to be a world
leading expert on a topic whilst also constantly being bombarded with questions
that make you feel stupid?</p>
<p><strong>I loved my PhD experience, but I am so glad it is dead</strong>. I cannot in good faith
suggest that anyone take that path, if they have an alternative.</p>
<h2 id="respect-makes-a-world-of-difference">Respect makes a world of difference!</h2>
<p>It had always been my dream to pursue academia, and I never even considered
leaving. Until I did.</p>
<p>These thoughts and feelings are only able to come to the surface because I am
now free of the academic system.</p>
<p>Allow me to elaborate: when in academia I was constantly encouraged to perform
outreach, to teach and to participate with the wider community&hellip; BUT NOT DURING
WORKING HOURS. So when did they expect this? And when people did these extra
activities there was always the question of &ldquo;will this damage your research?&rdquo;.
Academia expects everything from you, and then asks for more.</p>
<p>When I migrated to academia-adjacent work I was taken aback by the encouragement
I received to pursue the things that made me happy:</p>
<ul>
<li>&ldquo;Can I arrange this hackathon?&rdquo; - &ldquo;Yes Aoife, let us know how we can support you&rdquo;.</li>
<li>&ldquo;Can I use work time to do data science work with this relevant charity&rdquo; - &ldquo;Sure&rdquo;.</li>
<li>&ldquo;Can I apply for these grants?&rdquo; - &ldquo;Of course, we will happily support you&rdquo;.</li>
</ul>
<p>Respect. That&rsquo;s the difference. My new workplace respects me, they make me feel
like what I say and do matters. They prove this by backing me. The same things
are felt in how they respect thoughts and opinions about work projects too.</p>
<h2 id="i-always-dreamed-of-living-in-a-city">I always dreamed of living in a city</h2>
<p>When I first read The Great Gatsby I was obsessed with the character. Perhaps I
missed the points about obsessive love and the destruction that it can bring.
What I saw was someone who saw the world how they wanted it to be and then made
it so.</p>
<p>A large part of this was the running away from home. My final stage of running
away is making it to London.</p>
<p>To shopping, to sitting in cafés, eating good food and socialising. Late night
trains and lights which never go out. The 3 am shouts and the 6 am door slams.
These are the things I&rsquo;ve craved for.</p>
<h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1>
<p>Sorry for the rambling. I started writing this in one mood and then fell to
another. Thanks Bon Iver. They have that effect, wouldn&rsquo;t you agree?</p>
<p>Anyway, life is really good. I wish this post could be sent backwards and that I
could read it a year ago. I needed it then.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Top 5 Games 2021</title><link>/posts/top-5-games-2021/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2021 17:40:54 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/top-5-games-2021/</guid><description>About this list! Before I list my top games of 2021 I want to make clear that this is purely a list of the games which I enjoyed the most in 2021. Meaning a few of the games released quite a few years prior. These aren&amp;rsquo;t reviews, and I will avoid spoilers!
(Here is a full video of this article on my YouTube channel)
# 5. Chivalry 2. Most nights, when I have time to play games, I don&amp;rsquo;t have the energy for story heavy or intense gameplay sessions.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="about-this-list">About this list!</h2>
<p>Before I list my top games of 2021 I want to make clear that this is purely a list of the games which I enjoyed the most in 2021. Meaning a few of the games released quite a few years prior. These aren&rsquo;t reviews, and I will avoid spoilers!</p>
<p>(Here is a full video of this article on my YouTube channel)</p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9BS--eerCXc"><img src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/9BS--eerCXc/0.jpg" alt="Full Video of article"></a></p>
<h2 id="-5-chivalry-2"># 5. Chivalry 2.</h2>
<p>Most nights, when I have time to play games, I don&rsquo;t have the energy for story heavy or intense gameplay sessions. Chivalry is simply a fun game which I can switch off my brain and swing a sword for 30 minutes (or several hours). Since the release of the first game a few other studios have attempted to recreate the medieval melee multiplayer with various degrees of success. Playing these imitation games felt just like that, a shallow attempt to recapture the initial magic of the first game. But, Chivalry 2 has rekindled my love for this style of game and the simple to pick up and hard to master gameplay is perfect for what I want in this style of game.</p>
<h2 id="-4-gta-san-andreas-2004"># 4. GTA: San Andreas 2004</h2>
<p>Back before Rockstar announced that the PS2 era of GTA games would receive &ldquo;remasters&rdquo; I had found myself watching a lot of speedruns. One category in particular which I found most enjoyable was the GTA:SA runs at events like GDQ. Remembering that SA&rsquo;s Xbox 360 incarnation was backwards compatible I picked it back up myself. Not to speedrun, but just to enjoy. I ended up completing about 60% of the main game before the &ldquo;remasters&rdquo; were released. Something about these updates coming out killed my enthusiasm for a bit, but I do plan on getting back into this game soon and finishing it off!</p>
<p>Mostly this game is a nostalgia trip for me. I remember when GTA games came out I had to wait for my dad to complete them first to &ldquo;make sure they were appropriate&rdquo;, now I realise that he was just wanting to complete the game in peace before 11 year old me hogged the PS2 and messed up his saves.</p>
<h2 id="-3-star-wars-knights-of-the-old-republic"># 3. Star Wars: Knights of the old republic</h2>
<p>Oddly enough, this game too came out around the same time as GTA:SA. As I wasn&rsquo;t a PC gamer at the time (still not really), nor did I have an Xbox this game never crossed my radar. I am a massive fan of Star Wars, I love episode 1, all 6 movies really, and even read some of the older expanded universe books! Yet, I was never inspired to pick up and try out this game.</p>
<p>Enter the Switch port. This isn&rsquo;t the perfect place to play this game, but for me a game being on the Switch just makes it more likely that I&rsquo;ll get into it!</p>
<h2 id="-2-persona-5-royal"># 2. Persona 5 Royal</h2>
<p>When I was going through my played games for 2021 I took a double take when I saw that I played Persona 5 Royal this year. In a strange way this game feels like a life I used to live. Looking at gameplay makes me miss characters more than any other media franchise ever has. Even Morgana grew on me towards the end.</p>
<p>The minute to minute gameplay of Persona is not the most exciting and planning to go study or hangout with friends afterschool is hardly mentally challenging but by the end of a persona game you will have given a lot to the character you play and even after 120 hours you&rsquo;ll never be ready to leave.</p>
<h2 id="-1-hitman-3"># 1. Hitman 3</h2>
<p>IO Interactive have done a beautiful thing with their Hitman trilogy. Making all the levels work in the updated engine was a stroke of genius. Most of my time in Hitman 3 was probably spent in Hitman 1&rsquo;s Sapienza or else in Hitman 2&rsquo;s Whittleton Creek levels. The developers still managed to innovate in some interesting ways, such as the murder mystery roleplaying and the VR. The VR worked so much better than I could have imagined too.</p>
<p>Hitman 3 isn&rsquo;t just a stealth game, it&rsquo;s a puzzle game. I spent so much time just toying around with mechanics, setting up traps and watching how NPCs react to different scenarios. Shooting a target with a tranquillizer dart and having them fall into a body of water and drown has to be one of the funniest moments in gaming for me. This game really understands its audience</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve seen that IOI are aiming to bring us more Hitman content in 2022 and I cannot wait to have more reasons to jump into this game!</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>A review of Marvel Champions the Living Card Game</title><link>/posts/marvel-champions-review/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2021 19:23:09 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/marvel-champions-review/</guid><description>Intro Marvel champions is the latest living card game (LCG) from fantasy flight games. If you are familiar with other entries in this series of games, such as Arkham Horror The Card Game, then not much introduction is needed. These games come with a core set that gets you started and allows/encourages you to expand your gameplay through additional expansion packs. Unlike some games on the market, these LCGs and their expansions are not randomised and you always know what you’re getting in your box/card pack.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="intro">Intro</h2>
<p><img src="/images/mv0.png" alt="img0"></p>
<p>Marvel champions is the latest living card game (LCG) from fantasy flight games. If you are familiar with other entries in this series of games, such as Arkham Horror The Card Game, then not much introduction is needed. These games come with a core set that gets you started and allows/encourages you to expand your gameplay through additional expansion packs. Unlike some games on the market, these LCGs and their expansions are not randomised and you always know what you’re getting in your box/card pack.</p>
<p>In Marvel Champions you can play solo or cooperatively with 2-4 players, unlike past LCG’s such as Arkham Horror only a single core set is needed for 4 players. Included in the box are 5 classic marvel heroes: Iron Man, Captain Marvel, Spider-Man, Black Panther and She-Hulk. Each player chooses a hero and builds a deck of cards (Spider-Man and Captain Marvel come with pre-build decks that let you jump straight to playing!). With your deck you are thrown into some classic comic action and tasked with bringing down a big bad, along with their minions. The loop of gameplay is fairly straight-forward, players will take turns playing cards from their hands, villains will play cards from their ‘encounter’ deck and build up a threat meter, if at any time the players lose all their health or the villain amasses enough threat tokens you lose, if the heroes reduce the enemy’s health, then they win. It’s a little more involved and can take a few turns to memorise the pattern, but there are some handy reference cards to keep you right.</p>
<p><img src="/images/mv1.png" alt="img1"></p>
<h2 id="gameplay">Gameplay</h2>
<p>For this review we played 2-player, which Board Game Geek (BGG) voters suggest is one of the best player counts.  So be aware of this if you do plan on playing with larger groups. I had played before looking at these votes on BGG and I can imagine them to be pretty accurate. The game scales by multiplying actions of the enemy by player count. For example, during the enemy phase each player is delt a card from the encounter deck, more players = more chaos by the villain. At two players I never felt like my turn was too far away, at 4 I could easily see this becoming an issue where the enemy makes such a large leap forward between my turns that I may feel a bit weak and helpless (5 damage in a turn on a 40 health Ultron feels impactful, on 80 health Ultron it could be demoralising). But I haven’t played this way so I cannot do more than speculate to the reasons for BGG votes.</p>
<p><img src="/images/mv2.png" alt="img2"></p>
<p>One of the superhero inspired features of this game is that each character card is double-sided. In an almost perfect metaphor one side of the card is the powerful smashing, blasting, evil thwarting hero and the other is the person behind the mask. Once per turn a player may flip between these two forms, many cards in your deck will specify which form to be in, adding additional strategy and planning requirement (e.g., Peter Parker isn’t going to be allowed to deliver a web-swinging kick to Rhino, and Spider-Man can’t visit Aunt May for some Healing!).</p>
<p><img src="/images/mv3.png" alt="img3"></p>
<p>In addition to these alter-egos each player will submit an obligation card into the enemy deck at the start of the game, along with having a unique adversary on standby which may show up if a specific encounter card is drawn. These additional elements go a long way towards making each character feel unique and making the game feel re-playable.</p>
<h2 id="with-great-power">With Great Power</h2>
<p>My biggest fear going into this game, and the main reason I held of diving in for so long (despite being a life-long gamer and Marvel geek) was that the uniqueness of the heroes would not transfer well to this style of game whilst maintaining the balance required. The cynic in me also thought how easy it would be for Fantasy Flight Games to make this a pay-to-win fiasco by adding in over-powered heroes in sold-separately expansions. I can safely say this fear was removed from a single playthrough. A great example of hero uniqueness can be seen in Iron Man, this character begins the game with a hand-size limit of 1 card, but through that classic Tony Stark attitude you upgrade and ramp yourself up to be a Stark-tech certified power-house.</p>
<p><img src="/images/mv4.png" alt="img4"></p>
<p>Each of the characters we played as felt thematic and useful to our two-player team. That’s not to say that some characters aren’t more fun. I definitely had more fun with Iron-Man than say She-Hulk and if you’re experienced with card games then some heroes may feel a bit simple.  This does work to the games benefit at times, allowing you to play with a group who are very into Marvel but new to card games.</p>
<p>Additionally, in terms of character selection I was very happy to see a diverse set of heroes in the core set, and available in expansions. Having more of a choice in who I want to play as and the role I want to undertake is always welcome.</p>
<h2 id="an-ant-has-no-quarrel-with-a-boot">An ant has no quarrel with a boot</h2>
<p>So far in this review we haven’t mentioned much about the enemies you will encounter in this game. When I think about enemies in cooperative board games I think of the simple like in Pandemic where you know pretty well what will happen each turn and of Gloomhaven where enemies have a much deeper and harder to predict move set. Marvel Champions sits somewhere in the lower-middle of that range. Most of the time I knew the enemy was going to attack and deal damage to us or they would generate some threat tokens. Perhaps I expect too much complexity and I am spoiled by some other games. Conversely, the relative simplicity in enemy moves does make this a much easier game to play and doesn’t require one player to play 2 roles (the AI and their hero).</p>
<p>Where the game does add a little bit of variety is in the side-schemes. The encounter deck can contain a few of these cards which create additional objectives for the heroes to clear. For example, civilians may come under attack which requires heroes to solve before they can get back to the main mission or a bomb scare may cause additional threat tokens to be generated per turn. These do cause an additional stress for the players, but they feel so pressing that there’s not really an option to ignore them, so if anything, they take agency away from the player(s).</p>
<p><img src="/images/mv5.png" alt="img5"></p>
<p>The game does offer some basic methods to increase difficulty. Mostly this is in the choice to add additional cards or swap out easier cards for harder ones. In the introductory scenario where you fight Rhino you face up against Rhino I and Rhino II, for a harder challenge you can swap I for III and start at II. Extra threats can be added to the encounter deck so there’s always a chance of harder minions or sub-threats to turn up.</p>
<p><img src="/images/mv6.png" alt="img6"></p>
<h2 id="components-box-and-table-space">Components, box and table space</h2>
<p>As far as game components go, those that come with Marvel Champions are pretty good. Card quality is good and the comic-style artwork of the cards is fantastic and on-point, tokens are cardboard too and the health trackers are self-assembled and work well. Fully setting up the game for two players can take up more space on a table than you would initially expect from a card game, some enemy encounters can create lots of minions which quickly take up a lot of room (for some reason the game uses player cards as minions during one fight and not just tokens, which would have made more sense to me).</p>
<p><img src="/images/mv7.png" alt="img7"></p>
<p>With these LCGs card management can be a huge annoyance and has for me previously being a barrier to getting a game to the table. I don’t want to play a game if 50% of my time is reorganising cards that have gotten shuffled in the box. In an almost monkey paw wish Fantasy Flight Games have added an insert into the game box for dividing cards, but give no dividers to actually make use of this. Whilst I wait for plastic dividers from Etsy I used some spare cardboard which does the job for now.</p>
<p><img src="/images/mv8.png" alt="img8"></p>
<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>Theme and presentation can really make or break a board game, previously I have struggled to get into LCG’s despite being huge fans of Lovecraftian and Tolkien worlds those games didn’t click with me. The comic aesthetic and simple message of “hit bad guys” instantly hooked me on this game. It’s not for everyone, but if you like card games or want to get into them and have a love for Marvel then this game is an easy recommend.</p>
<ul>
<li>Artwork: 5/5</li>
<li>Complexity: 3/5</li>
<li>Replayability: 4/5</li>
<li>Player interaction: 3/5</li>
<li>Component quality: 3/5</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Overall Score: 80</strong></p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Computational Modelling with Apple Silicon</title><link>/posts/m1modelling/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Nov 2021 15:15:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/m1modelling/</guid><description>Ever since Apple Silicon was announced I was enthralled and curious. Even as reviews and benchmarks came pouring in after the original M1 Macbook Pro, Mini and Air released I was skeptical. Working in research we often find that tools we depend on are ancient by computer standards, even worse is that some of them are either difficult to build/update or are closed source (or worse still, written in PERL!). Which highlights my major fear of Apple&amp;rsquo;s new direction, I was initially terrified that almost all of my pipelines and tools would die in x86 and I would be forced to migrate to, ugh, Windows.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ever since Apple Silicon was announced I was enthralled and curious. Even as reviews and benchmarks came pouring in after the original M1 Macbook Pro, Mini and Air released I was skeptical. Working in research we often find that tools we depend on are ancient by computer standards, even worse is that some of them are either difficult to build/update or are closed source (or worse still, written in PERL!).
Which highlights my major fear of Apple&rsquo;s new direction, I was initially terrified that almost all of my pipelines and tools would die in x86 and I would be forced to migrate to, ugh, Windows. This fear quickly subsided when a colleague in my office picked up a M1 Macbook and told me how easy it was for them to setup for data analysis/research. I then had the opportunity to test my curiosity about these new machines, I asked this friend of mine if he would run one of my example computational models. I was completely floored by the results of this request.</p>
<p>The results alone (which I&rsquo;ll go into after describing the models and the tests) were enough for me to request from my supervisor that I get an upgrade to a M1 myself.</p>
<h2 id="the-models">The Models</h2>
<p>I describe some examples of what I currently spend most of my time modelling in a previous <a href="/posts/narrow-escape/" title="Narrow Escapes">blog-post</a>.</p>
<p>Basically, I use random walk models to establish transport times for molecules in and out of plant cells.</p>
<p>These models aren&rsquo;t too hard to run, maybe 10 seconds computation time per one on an iMac Intel 27inch (for reference). The difficulty comes in the repetition of them. We need to run a few thousand simulations and average across them in order to get an accurate result.</p>
<h2 id="tests">Tests</h2>
<p>Using our Narrow Escape Simulator package (<a href="https://github.com/AoifeHughes/NarrowEscapeSimulator">https://github.com/AoifeHughes/NarrowEscapeSimulator</a>) we ran 5 x repeats of 1000 simulations on a 2018 Intel i5 iMac 3.5Ghz and a MacBook M1 Pro.</p>
<h2 id="results">Results</h2>
<p>These results pretty much speak for themselves and need little elaboration:</p>
<p><img src="/images/m1_tests.png" alt="Results"></p>
<p>To put a number to it, the M1 Pro is about 364% faster at calculating the narrow escape models than the Intel iMac.</p>
<h2 id="why-is-this-important-to-me">Why is this important to me?</h2>
<p>Saving about 13 minutes might not seem like a big deal, but I run hundreds of these experiments with many configurations. Every variable change requires them to be re-run. Previously I relied heavily on high-performance computing to handle the volume of models I run, now I suspect I can do all of it locally, on a laptop no less.</p>
]]></content></item><item><title>Visualising World Temperature Data</title><link>/posts/temp-data/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Nov 2021 00:57:10 +0100</pubDate><guid>/posts/temp-data/</guid><description>I like to start with the end result of a project, just to show if this is what you&amp;rsquo;re looking for before you read:
Some caveats:
These data are limited to what a 10 second google search yielded (I found it on Kaggle) Data are approximately matched to country codes in order to streamline things Year range of data is very limited Code is written in an obtuse way in order to make clear what is happening There is little need for multiple lists matching data codes for example Some countries are missing data, easily solved with better country code matching and a better data source Libraries required for this:</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I like to start with the end result of a project, just to show if this is what you&rsquo;re looking for before you read:</p>


    <iframe src="/subfiles/temp.html" style="height: 700px; width: 100%;"></iframe>


<p>Some caveats:</p>
<ul>
<li>These data are limited to what a 10 second google search yielded (I found it on Kaggle)</li>
<li>Data are approximately matched to country codes in order to streamline things</li>
<li>Year range of data is very limited</li>
<li>Code is written in an obtuse way in order to make clear what is happening
<ul>
<li>There is little need for multiple lists matching data codes for example</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Some countries are missing data, easily solved with better country code matching and a better data source</li>
</ul>
<p>Libraries required for this:</p>
<ul>
<li>pandas</li>
<li>plotly</li>
<li>numpy (probably)</li>
<li>pycountry (because data source lacked these codes that plotly uses)</li>
</ul>
<p>With proper data, this should really be a country agnostic plot. I&rsquo;ll update this when I have time to find data&hellip;</p>
<p>Okay, so this pretty much works like any data analysis/visualization. First we load in the data,</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-python" data-lang="python"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#f92672">import</span> plotly.graph_objects <span style="color:#66d9ef">as</span> go
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#f92672">import</span> pandas <span style="color:#66d9ef">as</span> pd
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>df <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> pd<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>read_csv(<span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;temp_data.csv&#39;</span>)<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>melt(id_vars<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>[<span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;year&#39;</span>], var_name<span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;country&#39;</span>, value_name<span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;temperature&#39;</span>)</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>, because the data are column based we just have to melt it so that each country has a year and a temperature per row.</p>
<p>Using pycountry we can create a dictionary to match up country names in our data to their codes used in plotting per country,</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-python" data-lang="python"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#f92672">import</span> pycountry
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>keys <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> [list(pycountry<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>countries)[i]<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>alpha_3 <span style="color:#66d9ef">for</span> i <span style="color:#f92672">in</span> range(len(pycountry<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>countries))]
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>names <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> [list(pycountry<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>countries)[i]<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>name <span style="color:#66d9ef">for</span> i <span style="color:#f92672">in</span> range(len(pycountry<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>countries))]
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>conv <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> { v:k <span style="color:#66d9ef">for</span> k,v <span style="color:#f92672">in</span> zip(keys,names) }
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#66d9ef">def</span> <span style="color:#a6e22e">match_name</span>(x):
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    <span style="color:#66d9ef">try</span>:
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        <span style="color:#66d9ef">return</span> conv[x]
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    <span style="color:#66d9ef">except</span> <span style="color:#a6e22e">KeyError</span> <span style="color:#66d9ef">as</span> e:
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        <span style="color:#66d9ef">for</span>  n <span style="color:#f92672">in</span> names:
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>            <span style="color:#66d9ef">if</span> x <span style="color:#f92672">in</span> n:
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>                <span style="color:#66d9ef">return</span> conv[n]
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        <span style="color:#66d9ef">return</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;N/A&#39;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>df[<span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;codes&#39;</span>] <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> df<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>apply(<span style="color:#66d9ef">lambda</span> x: match_name(x[<span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;country&#39;</span>]), axis<span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#ae81ff">1</span>)</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>Finally, using plotly sliders, we can just create a Choropleth plot for each year, set it to not being visable and create a master figure out of them all.</p>
<p>And thats that.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-python" data-lang="python"><span style="display:flex;"><span>years <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> df[<span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;year&#39;</span>]<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>unique()
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>years<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>sort()
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>years_sliders <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> []
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#66d9ef">for</span> year <span style="color:#f92672">in</span> years:
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    tdf <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> df[df[<span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;year&#39;</span>] <span style="color:#f92672">==</span> year]
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    years_sliders<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>append(go<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>Choropleth(
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        visible<span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#66d9ef">False</span>,
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        locations <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> tdf[<span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;codes&#39;</span>],
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        z <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> tdf[<span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;temperature&#39;</span>],
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        text <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> tdf[<span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;country&#39;</span>],
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        colorscale <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;RdBu&#39;</span>,
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        autocolorscale<span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#66d9ef">True</span>,
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        reversescale<span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#66d9ef">False</span>,
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        marker_line_color<span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;darkgray&#39;</span>,
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        marker_line_width<span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#ae81ff">0.5</span>,
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        colorbar_tickprefix <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;C&#39;</span>,
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        colorbar_title <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;Temperature&#39;</span>,
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        zmin<span style="color:#f92672">=-</span>df[<span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;temperature&#39;</span>]<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>min(), zmax<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>df[<span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;temperature&#39;</span>]<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>max()
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    ))
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>fig <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> go<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>Figure(data<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>years_sliders)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>steps <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> []
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#66d9ef">for</span> i <span style="color:#f92672">in</span> range(len(years)):
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    step <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> dict(
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        method<span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;update&#34;</span>,
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        args<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>[{<span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;visible&#34;</span>: [<span style="color:#66d9ef">False</span>] <span style="color:#f92672">*</span> len(fig<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>data)},
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>              {<span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;title&#34;</span>: <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;Year: &#34;</span> <span style="color:#f92672">+</span> str(years[i])}],
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>              label<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>str(years[i])  <span style="color:#75715e"># layout attribute</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    )
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    step[<span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;args&#34;</span>][<span style="color:#ae81ff">0</span>][<span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;visible&#34;</span>][i] <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#66d9ef">True</span>  <span style="color:#75715e"># Toggle i&#39;th trace to &#34;visible&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    steps<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>append(step)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>sliders <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> [dict(
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    active<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>len(years),
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    currentvalue<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>{<span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;prefix&#34;</span>: <span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;Steps: &#34;</span>},
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    pad<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>{<span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;t&#34;</span>: <span style="color:#ae81ff">50</span>},
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    steps<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>steps,
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>)]
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>geo<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>dict(
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        showframe<span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#66d9ef">False</span>,
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        showcoastlines<span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#66d9ef">False</span>,
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        projection_type<span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#e6db74">&#39;orthographic&#39;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    )
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>fig<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>update_layout(
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    sliders<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>sliders,
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    geo<span style="color:#f92672">=</span>geo
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>fig<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>data[<span style="color:#ae81ff">0</span>]<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>visible <span style="color:#f92672">=</span> <span style="color:#66d9ef">True</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>fig<span style="color:#f92672">.</span>show()</span></span></code></pre></div>
]]></content></item><item><title>Narrow Escape Visualization</title><link>/posts/narrow-escape/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 13:45:50 +0100</pubDate><guid>/posts/narrow-escape/</guid><description>The Narrow Escape Problem is a bio physics problem which attempts to estimate how long it takes for a particle moving under Brownian motion to escape from a container with solid walls, where part of the wall is open.
Recently we published a software library for building narrow escape simulations. We also used this to discuss its use in determining the escape time for small molecules from plant cells.
I&amp;rsquo;ve recently been working with plotly to create interactive plots.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Narrow_escape_problem" title="NEP">Narrow Escape Problem</a> is a bio physics problem which attempts to estimate how long it takes for a particle moving under Brownian motion to escape from a container with solid walls, where part of the wall is open.</p>
<p>Recently <a href="https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.02072">we published a software library</a> for building narrow escape simulations. We also used this to discuss its use in determining the <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9440948">escape time for small molecules from plant cells</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve recently been working with <a href="https://plotly.com">plotly</a> to create interactive plots. With plotly I put together a little example of our simulation software which, I think, nicely explains the concept.</p>
<p>Below you can see our container cell in silvery-gray, a blue dot represents the part of the container which is free to escape through. By moving the slider you can see the random-walk path that the particle takes until it finally reaches the blue escape point.</p>
<p>(I also wrote this as I wanted an excuse to test out my new blog and how it handles these plotly graphs!)</p>


    <iframe src="/subfiles/NEP.html" style="height: 700px; width: 100%;"></iframe>


]]></content></item><item><title>Hello World</title><link>/posts/hello-world/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 13:28:26 +0100</pubDate><guid>/posts/hello-world/</guid><description>Hi, Thanks for coming to my new blog.
I hope to soon populate it with lots of fun things.</description><content type="html">&lt;p>Hi,
Thanks for coming to my new blog.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I hope to soon populate it with lots of fun things.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>