<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Aoife's Blog</title><link>/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Aoife's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 13:45:50 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Narrow Escape Visualization</title><link>/posts/narrow-escape/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 13:45:50 +0100</pubDate><guid>/posts/narrow-escape/</guid><description>The Narrow Escape Problem is a bio physics problem which attempts to estimate how long it takes for a particle moving under Brownian motion to escape from a container with solid walls, where part of the wall is open.
Recently we published a software library for building narrow escape simulations. We also used this to discuss its use in determining the escape time for small molecules from plant cells.
I&amp;rsquo;ve recently been working with plotly to create interactive plots.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Narrow_escape_problem" title="NEP">Narrow Escape Problem</a> is a bio physics problem which attempts to estimate how long it takes for a particle moving under Brownian motion to escape from a container with solid walls, where part of the wall is open.</p>
<p>Recently <a href="https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.02072">we published a software library</a> for building narrow escape simulations. We also used this to discuss its use in determining the <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9440948">escape time for small molecules from plant cells</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve recently been working with <a href="https://plotly.com">plotly</a> to create interactive plots. With plotly I put together a little example of our simulation software which, I think, nicely explains the concept.</p>
<p>Below you can see our container cell in silvery-gray, a blue dot represents the part of the container which is free to escape through. By moving the slider you can see the random-walk path that the particle takes until it finally reaches the blue escape point.</p>
<p>(I also wrote this as I wanted an excuse to test out my new blog and how it handles these plotly graphs!)</p>


    <iframe src="/subfiles/NEP.html" style="height: 700px; width: 100%;"></iframe>


]]></content></item><item><title>Hello World</title><link>/posts/hello-world/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 13:28:26 +0100</pubDate><guid>/posts/hello-world/</guid><description>Hi, Thanks for coming to my new blog.
I hope to soon populate it with lots of fun things.</description><content type="html">&lt;p>Hi,
Thanks for coming to my new blog.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I hope to soon populate it with lots of fun things.&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>